<component type="operating-system">
  <id>org.debian.debian</id>
  <name>Debian GNU/Linux</name>
  <summary>The universal operating system</summary>
  <description>
    <p>
      Debian is a free operating system (OS) for your computer.
      An operating system is the set of basic programs and utilities that make your computer run.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Debian Project is an association of individuals who have made common cause to create a free operating system.
      This operating system that we have created is called Debian.
    </p>
    <p>
      At the core of an operating system is the kernel.
      The kernel is the most fundamental program on the computer and does all the basic housekeeping and lets you start other programs.
      Debian systems use the Linux kernel. Linux is a piece of software started by Linus Torvalds and supported by thousands of
      programmers worldwide.
    </p>
  </description>

  <url type="homepage">https://www.debian.org/</url>
  <metadata_license>MIT</metadata_license>
  <developer id="org.debian">
    <name>The Debian Project</name>
  </developer>

  <icon type="stock">debian-logo.svg</icon>

  <releases>
    <release version="14" type="development" date="2025-08-14">
      <description>
        <p>The current development version of Debian.</p>
      </description>
    </release>

    <release version="13" date="2025-08-09">
      <description>
        <p>This release contains new features and changes:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Official support for the riscv64 architecture</li>
          <li>Hardening against ROP and COP/JOP attacks on amd64 and arm64</li>
          <li>HTTP Boot Support</li>
          <li>Improved manual pages translations</li>
          <li>Spell-checking support in Qt WebEngine web browsers</li>
          <li>64-bit time_t ABI transition</li>
          <li>Debian progress towards reproducible builds</li>
          <li>wcurl and HTTP/3 support in curl</li>
          <li>BDIC Binary Hunspell Dictionary Support</li>
          <li>Debian again ships with several desktop applications and environments.
            Among others it now includes the desktop environments GNOME 48, KDE Plasma 6.3, LXDE 13,
            LXQt 2.1.0, and Xfce 4.20.</li>
        </ul>
	<p>Check out the full release notes for a detailed overview of new features and changes.</p>
      </description>

      <url>https://www.debian.org/releases/trixie/release-notes/</url>
    </release>

    <release version="12" date="2023-06-10">
      <description>
        <p>This release contains many updated OS components and new features:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The non-free section of Debian's repositories has been split, with non-free Firmware packages
            being moved into a new section called non-free-firmware.
            Users who need packages from this section (basically, everyone running Debian on real hardware)
            may need to edit their <em>sources.list</em> files before upgrading to bookworm.</li>
          <li>Filesystems: apfs read/write support with apfsprogs / apfs-dkms, convert ntfs 2 btrfs with ntfs2btrfs</li>
          <li>New malloc implementation: mimalloc</li>
          <li>Kernel SMB server: ksmbd-tools</li>
        </ul>
	<p>It also introduces some notable changes:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>GRUB bootloader packages will by default no longer run os-prober to look for other
            operating systems on a computer when generating boot menus.
            Users with dual-boot systems may configure this using dpkg-reconfigure on the package
            in use (most likely grub-pc or grub-efi-amd64)</li>
          <li>The use of bash as /bin/sh is no longer supported. /bin/sh will be changed (if necessary)
            to point to dash (which has been the default configuration for many releases).
            The effects and risks of manually changing the /bin/sh symlink are not known at this time.</li>
          <li>The libpam-ldap and libnss-ldap packages have been removed due to lack of upstream activity;
            libpam-ldapd and libnss-ldapd provide updated equivalent functionality.</li>
          <li>This release only supports the merged-usr root filesystem layout.</li>
          <li>A syslog daemon, such as rsyslog, is no longer installed by default; the systemd journalctl
            utility is available to review logs. If desired, rsyslog and other syslog daemons are still
            available to be installed manually; search for system-log-daemon packages.</li>
          <li>The systemd package has demoted systemd-timesyncd from Depends to Recommends.
            Thus, minimal installations no longer include an NTP client.
            Installations with the default "standard system utilities" software selected,
            will install systemd-timesyncd. Alternate NTP programs may be installed manually;
            search for time-daemon packages(which doesn't work with apt.</li>
          <li>The tempfile and rename.ul programs have been removed. Any scripts which use either of these
            commands will need to be changed. Suitable replacements are mktemp and file-rename respectively.</li>
          <li>The which program has been deprecated, and writes a warning to standard error (but still works,
            so long as stderr is not being captured along with stdout).
            Shell script writers are advised to use command -v instead. Interactive bash shell users are
            advised to use type, or type -a. In zsh which is already a shell builtin, so interactive zsh
            users are not affected, same thing for csh and its derivative tcsh.</li>
        </ul>
	<p>Check out the full release notes for a detailed overview of new features and changes.</p>
      </description>

      <url>https://www.debian.org/releases/bookworm/amd64/release-notes/</url>
    </release>

    <release version="11" date="2021-08-14">
      <description>
        <p>This release contains many updated OS components, including but not limited to:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>GNOME 3.38, KDE Plasma 5.20, LXDE 11, LXQt 0.16, MATE 1.24, and Xfce 4.16</li>
          <li>Linux kernel from the 5.10 series</li>
          <li>GNU Compiler Collection (default compiler) 10.2</li>
          <li>LLVM/Clang toolchain 9.0.1 and 11.0.1 (default)</li>
          <li>OpenSSH 8.4p1</li>
          <li>Perl 5.32</li>
          <li>Python 3.9.1</li>
          <li>Rustc 1.48</li>
          <li>Samba 4.13</li>
          <li>and many more</li>
        </ul>
	<p>A lot of new features are also provided:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Driverless scanning and printing</li>
          <li>New <code>open</code> command as a convenience alias to <code>xdg-open</code></li>
          <li>Control groups v2</li>
          <li>Persistent systemd journal</li>
          <li>New Fcitx 5 Input Method</li>
          <li>Kernel support for exFAT</li>
          <li>Improved man page translations</li>
          <li>and many more</li>
        </ul>
	<p>Check out the full release notes for a detailed overview of new features and changes.</p>
      </description>

      <url>https://www.debian.org/releases/bullseye/amd64/release-notes/</url>
    </release>

    <release version="10" date="2019-07-06">
      <description>
        <p>
          This release of Debian  now supports UEFI Secure Boot, has AppArmor enabled by default, uses LUKS2 as the default LUKS format,
          and uses Wayland for the GNOME desktop session by default.
        </p>
        <p>
          Linux kernel 4.19 is included, as well as GNOME 3.30, KDE Plasma 5.14, LXDE 0.99.2, LXQt 0.14, MATE 1.20, Xfce 4.12 and Cinnamon 3.8.
        </p>
      </description>
    </release>

    <release version="9" date="2017-07-17" date_eol="2020-07-17">
      <description>
        <p>Now contains the Linux kernel 4.9, GNOME 3.22, KDE Plasma 5, LibreOffice 5.2 and Qt 5.7. LXQt has been added.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
